Finding Aid for Marketing and Communications (University of Michigan) records, 1950-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Marketing and Communications (University of Michigan) records 1950-1999 1970-1999
University of Michigan. Marketing and Communications.
03102 Bimu B6 2
The Marketing Communications office offers publicity and announcement services for the University of Michigan. They incorporate graphic design, editorial services, website creation, and project planning to assist campus units with the creation of brochures, bulletins, websites, posters, event programs, and recruiting materials. The Marketing Communications record group contains a few early records of the department however the bulk of the materials include sample products created by the office and photographic images used to create their publications. The photographs contain University of Michigan images including departmental programs, buildings, campus scenes, and faculty portraits.
5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received by Marketing Communications (donor no. 8938 ) through several accessions from February 2000 to April 2003.
The record group is open without restriction.
Marketing Communications originated through a subtle shifting of university ownership for its publicity role. A predecessor to the current unit was the Publications Office, once in charge of designing and publishing university-related publications. They originally created and disseminated University Relations publications, including the Proceedings of the Board of Regents, the University of Michigan Bulletin series, commencement programs, and university-wide recruiting materials. They also produced publications for individual university units for special events or serial production. The goal of the Office of University Publications was "effective communication in print." (Administrative Records, 1968 Policies and Procedures, Box 1)
As the university grew, boundaries adjusted to accommodate additional needs and responsibilities of the university's units and administration. The Publications Office underwent several leadership alterations throughout their history. Their original administrative body, the Director of University Relations, became the Vice President for University Relations in 1964. This title was adjusted to reflect its responsibility for monetary support to become the Vice President for University Relations and Development in 1969. The office redefined itself once again when the university's financial difficulties forced a greater emphasis on fundraising and development during the 1980s. It became the Vice President for Development and Communications in 1985. In 1988, the office was further broken down into Vice President for Development and Vice President for University Relations. The current Marketing Communications office reports to the Vice President for Communications, one of the three units created out of the previous University Relations vice presidency in 2001.
While still active with commencement and recruitment materials, Marketing Communications has otherwise diversified and expanded their operations from their preceding incarnation, focusing on additional services and multimedia presentation. Marketing Communications currently provides the University of Michigan community with custom products and services to advertise and promote campus programs and events. The office offers consultations, project planning assistance, graphic and website design, and editorial services. Print and digital products include brochures for departments and special events, announcements, posters, invitations, stationary and cards, class bulletins, campus maps, periodicals, event programs, logos, banners, conference brochures, recruiting mailers, annual reports, videos, and websites. A small sample of their creations include the Faculty and Staff Directory, University Profile, LSA Magazine, Business School's Alumni Relations Website (http://www.bus.umich.edu/alumni), and the M Card logo.
The Marketing Communications record group is divided into three series including Administrative Records, Products, and Visual Materials. Materials within the Products series were sampled to produce a representative body of the office's work. Some items were removed to existing publication record groups. Many photographs within the Visual Materials series originated from University of Michigan News and Information Services. These items were removed from the Marketing Communications records because they can be found within the News and Information Services record group at the Bentley Historical Library.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Marketing Communications.; University of Michigan--Campus.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
- Administrative Records
  Administrative Records (1968-1987) consisting of three folders. The series sheds light on the origins of the Marketing Communications office. The policies and procedures are the record group's link to past incarnations of the unit. It includes organizational charts, job descriptions, office roles, and procedures for standard activities within the Office of University Publications. These records reveal not only procedural and focus changes between the offices but also the dramatic differences in the use of technology and today's focus on multimedia communications. The Undergraduate Recruitment Literature Committee minutes and correspondence reveals a time when admissions advertisement played a larger role within the office's mission.
  - Policies and Procedures 1968-1978 (Box 1)
  - Undergraduate Recruitment Literature Committee 1983-1987, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Products
  The Products series (1991-1992) documents materials created by Marketing Communications within a two-year time span. The products are arranged by format and include posters, invitations, booklets, flyers, publications, school bulletins, stationery, event programs, and development materials. The miscellaneous folder contains such items as greeting cards, book labels, and logos.
  - Booklets
    - 1991 (Box 1)
    - 1992 (Box 1)
  - Brochures 1992 (Box 1)
  - Bulletins
    - 1991 (Box 1)
    - 1992 (Box 1)
  - Campaign Materials
    - 1991 (Box 1)
    - 1992 (Box 1)
  - Flyers
    - 1991 (Box 1)
    - 1992 (Box 1)
  - Invitations 1992 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - 1991 (Box 1)
    - 1992 (Box 1)
  - Periodicals
    - 1991 (Box 1)
    - 1992 (Box 1)
  - Posters
    - 1991 (Folder 1)
    - 1992 (Folder 1)
  - Programs
    - 1991 (Box 2)
    - 1992 (Box 2)
  - Special Project: The Chemical Sciences Project: A Notebook of Commemorative Naming Opportunities (Box 2)
  - Stationery
    - 1991 (Box 2)
    - 1992 (Box 2)
- Visual Materials
  The largest series within the Marketing Communications record group is Visual Materials (1950s-1999). It contains photographs, slides, negatives, drawings, and videotapes used in publications and communications. The first subseries, drawings, contains oversized original sketches of past University of Michigan Presidents by Allan Mardon. The Photographs subseries consists mainly of University of Michigan faculty and staff photographs along with a smaller group of photos of campus buildings and events and aerial views of campus. The final subseries is comprised of videotapes produced by Marketing Communications.
  - Drawings
    - University of Michigan Presidents (Henry Philip Tappan to Harold Tafler Shapiro) 1980s (Folder 1)
  - Photographs
    The Photographs subseries contains two folders of images of Ann Arbor (ca. 19 80-1988) and Detroit (1969-1994) and 3.5 linear feet of University of Michigan images, mainly faculty and staff portraits. There are two groupings within the Faculty and Staff heading. Folders listed under A Legacy of Commitment to Scholarship: Named Faculty Positions at the University of Michigan contain the photographs used in the creation of the publication. They are arranged by department. The remainder of the faculty and staff photographs are general portrait files arranged alphabetically. Most of these images are from the 1980s although there are few exact dates on the photographs. General subject files comprise the rest of the photographic images. They are listed alphabetically by topic. Dates were listed when identified on the images.
    - Cities
      - Ann Arbor circa 1980-1988 (Box 2)
      - Detroit 1969-1994 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan
      - Faculty and Staff Portraits
        - A Legacy of Commitment to Scholarship: Named Faculty Positions at the University of Michigan, 1986
          - College of Architecture and Urban Planning
            - Birkerts, Gunnar (Box 2)
          - School of Business Administration
            - Bagozzi, Richard P. (Box 2)
            - Benton, Dwight F. (Box 2)
            - Harris, Nicki (Box 2)
            - Harris, J. Ira (Box 2)
            - Imhoff, Eugene (Box 2)
            - Kim, E. Han (Box 2)
            - Kinney, Jr., William R. (Box 2)
            - Spivey, W. Allen (Box 2)
          - School of Dentistry
            - Ash, Jr., Major M. (Box 2)
            - Browne, Robert W. (Box 2)
          - School of Education
            - Morse, William C. (Box 2)
          - College of Engineering
            - Anderson, J. Reid (Box 2)
            - Anderson, Polly (Box 2)
            - Kammash, Terry (Box 2)
            - Vennema, Ame and Catherine (Box 2)
          - Law School
            - Kamisar, Yale (Box 2)
            - McCree, Wade (Box 2)
            - Reed, John W. (Box 2)
            - Smith, Alene and Allan (Box 2)
          - College of Literature, Science, and the Arts
            - Alexander, Richard D. (Box 2)
            - D'Arms, John (Box 2)
            - Dawson, William R. (Box 2)
            - Douven, Elizabeth A. (Box 2)
            - Foesyth, Ilene (Box 2)
            - Goic, Cedomil (Box 2)
            - Kade, Max (Box 2)
            - Kelly, William C. (Box 2)
            - Nelson, James B. (Box 2)
            - Palmer, Alice Freeman (Box 2)
            - Palmer, Jeff (Box 2)
            - Pulgram, Ernst (Box 2)
            - Sarmiento, Domingo Faustino (Box 2)
            - Shaffer, Robert L. (Box 2)
            - Thurman, Arthur F. (Box 2)
            - Varian, Hal R. (Box 2)
            - Wilder, Raymond L. (Box 2)
            - Zajonc, Robert (Box 2)
          - Medical School
            - Imperiale, Michael (Box 2)
            - Martel, William (Box 2)
            - Prochownik, Edward (Box 2)
            - Searle, John G. (Box 2)
            - Turcotte, Jeremiah (Box 2)
          - School of Natural Resources
            - Hales, David (Box 2)
          - School of Public Health
            - Searle, John G. (Box 2)
              (see Medical School folder)
            - Sinai, Nathan (Box 2)
          - School of Social Work
            - Dunham, Arthur (Box 2)
            - Vinter, Robert D. (Box 2)
        - Individual Portraits
          - A
            - Alexander, R. (Box 2)
            - Allen, Francis A. 1984 (Box 2)
            - Altermatt, Maureen 1988 (Box 2)
            - Altman, Robert (Box 2)
            - Amoruso, John (Box 2)
            - Angell, Robert Cooley (Box 2)
            - Ash, Jr., Major M. 1985 (Box 2)
            - Ashe, A. (Box 2)
            - Attwood, J. (Box 2)
          - B
            - Bang, Jina (Box 2)
            - Banks, Peter (Box 2)
            - Barker, John (Box 2)
            - Bartell (Box 2)
            - Barton, B. F. (Box 2)
            - Bassett, Leslie 1977 (Box 2)
            - Beasley, William R. (Box 2)
            - Bedford, Neal 1975 (Box 2)
            - Birkerts, Gunnar (Box 2)
            - Blackmar, Charles (Box 2)
            - Bollinger, Lee 1989 (Box 2)
            - Brinkerhoff, James (Box 2)
            - Brodsky, Joseph (Box 2)
            - Brown, Donald (Box 2)
            - Bruder, Joseph A. (Box 2)
          - C
            - Cantor, Nancy (Box 2)
            - Carver, Keith (Box 2)
            - Cedomic, Goic (Box 2)
            - Chambers, R. (Box 2)
            - Chastain, Walter (Box 2)
            - Chesler, Mark (Box 2)
            - Clark, Janice (Box 2)
            - Coller, Frederick A. (Box 2)
            - Cook, Donald C. (Box 2)
            - Converse, Philip E. 1979 (Box 2)
            - Cooley, Charles H. (Box 2)
            - Cooley, Thomas (Box 2)
            - Coon, Minor J. (Box 2)
            - Cosovich, Jon (Box 2)
            - Coucouvanis (Box 2)
            - Cox (Box 2)
            - Culp, Jerome 1989 (Box 2)
            - Culp, William H. (Box 2)
          - D
            - Danos, Paul (Box 2)
            - D'Arms, John (Box 2)
            - Dashner, Mike 1993 (Box 2)
            - Davidson, William (Box 2)
            - Davis, P. (Box 2)
            - Dawson, William R. (Box 2)
            - Day, Edmund Ezra (Box 2)
            - Debrodt, R. (Box 2)
            - Deitch, Laurence B. 1993 (Box 2)
            - Delbanco, Nicholas 1984 (Box 2)
            - de Yound, Romig (Box 2)
            - Dice (Box 2)
            - Dilts, Jr., Preston V. (Box 2)
            - Donabedion, Avedis 1975 (Box 2)
            - Donahue, Thomas (Box 2)
            - Elizabeth Douvan (Box 2)
            - du Boisrouvray, Albina (Box 2)
            - Dunham, Arthur (Box 2)
            - du Plessix, Francine (Box 2)
            - Dvorak (Box 2)
          - E
            - Ege, Seyham N. (Box 2)
            - Eisenstein, Elizabeth 1984 (Box 2)
            - Eisenstein (Box 2)
            - Elliot, Warren (Box 2)
            - Else, Gerald F. (Box 2)
            - Estep, Samuel (Box 2)
          - F
            - Faeth, Gerard M. (Box 2)
            - Farri, Fedele (Box 2)
            - Felheim, Marvin (Box 2)
            - Fine, Sidney 1985 (Box 2)
            - Flannery, Kent, circa 1984 (Box 2)
            - Fogler, H. Scott (Box 2)
            - Ford, Gerald (Box 2)
            - Forman, Robert (Box 2)
            - Forsyth, Ilene 1984 (Box 2)
            - Fowlder, Erika (see Gordon) (Box 2)
            - Francis (Box 2)
            - Frasca, Robert (Box 2)
            - Freedman, David Noel 1977 (Box 2)
            - Freedman, R. (Box 2)
            - Freehling, Norman (Box 2)
            - French 1982 (Box 2)
            - French, David (Box 2)
            - Frost, Olivia (Box 2)
            - Frumhoff, Brian (Box 2)
            - Frye, Billy E. (Box 2)
          - G
            - Gannon (Box 2)
            - Gehring, Frederick W. (Box 2)
            - Genovese, Eugene 1989 (Box 2)
            - Gidwitz, Teri (Box 2)
            - Gordon (Box 2)
            - Gordon, Jesse (Box 2)
            - Gordus (Box 2)
            - Griffin (Box 2)
            - Griffin, Clare E. 1967 (Box 2)
            - Griffith, John R. 1979 (Box 2)
            - Grotrian (Box 2)
            - Gupta, Sansay (Simon) (Box 2)
          - H
            - Hales, David 1984 (Box 2)
            - Harris, J. Ira and Nicki (Box 2)
            - Harris, Robert 1989 (Box 2)
            - Harrison, George B. (Box 2)
            - Hart, Phil (Box 2)
            - Hartwig, Gene (Box 2)
            - Hartz, Will (Box 2)
            - Heller, C. (Box 2)
            - Hildebrandt, Theophil Henry (Box 2)
            - Hilpon (Box 2)
            - Horst, Margaret M. (Box 2)
            - Hobbs, William H. (Box 2)
            - Hochster, Melvin (Box 2)
            - Hoffman, Jim 1988 (Box 2)
            - Hofstadter, Douglas (Box 2)
            - Horne, Andy (Box 2)
            - Horny, Karen L. (Box 2)
            - Howard, June (Box 2)
            - Hubbard, Daren E. (Box 2)
            - Hurtado, Sylvia (Box 2)
          - I-J
            - Imhoff, E. (Box 2)
            - Israel, Jerold H. 1984 (Box 2)
            - Jackson, John (Box 2)
            - Jacobs, Francis 1989 (Box 2)
            - Jacobson, Harold K. (Box 2)
            - Jay (Box 2)
            - Jerry, Robert H. (Box 2)
            - Johnson, Henry 1982 (Box 2)
          - K
            - Kade, Max G. (Box 2)
            - Kahn, Douglas A. 1984 (Box 2)
            - Karnapp, Bruce 1992 (Box 2)
            - Kalisch, B. (Box 2)
            - Kamisar, Yale, ca. 1975-1984 (Box 2)
            - Kammash, T. (Box 2)
            - Kauper, Paul G. (Box 2)
            - Kauper, Thomas E. (Box 2)
            - Kelley, William (Box 2)
            - Kelly, William C. (Box 2)
            - Keniston, Hayward (Box 2)
            - Kennedy, Frank (Box 2)
            - Kim, E. Han 1984 (Box 2)
            - King, Jean 1989 (Box 2)
            - Kinney, Jr., William R. (Box 2)
            - Klein, Maynard (Box 2)
            - Knott, John R. (Box 2)
            - Kopelman (Box 2)
            - Kozolchyk, Boris (Box 2)
            - Kuchick, John (Box 2)
            - Kunce-Field, Julie (Box 2)
          - L
            - Landgrebe, D. (Box 2)
            - Lehman, Paul (Box 2)
            - Leith, Emmett N. (Box 2)
            - Leung, Cindy 1988 (Box 2)
            - Lewis, Edith (Box 2)
            - Libby, Robert 1981 (Box 2)
            - Lipschutz, Susan S. (Box 2)
            - Luciano 1983 (Box 2)
          - M
            - Manohan, Tom (Box 2)
            - Manoogian, Alex (Box 2)
            - Marks, William (see Norman W. Thompson) (Box 2)
            - Martin, Claude 1984 (Box 2)
            - Martin, Louis E. (Box 2)
            - Matlock, John (Box 2)
            - Maynard, Olivia P. (Box 2)
            - McCracken, Paul (Box 2)
            - McCree, Jr., Wade H. (Box 2)
            - McGowan, Rebecca (Box 2)
            - McKenzie, Roderick D. (Box 2)
            - Meil, Jack (see David Schoem) 1988 (Box 2)
            - Michaeloski, P. (Box 2)
            - Mitshkun, Mark 1989 (Box 2)
            - Modine (Box 2)
            - Moody, Charles (Box 2)
            - Moore, Earl V. (Box 2)
            - Moreno, Bernie 1988 (Box 2)
            - Morse (Box 2)
            - Moser, Karlos (Box 2)
            - Motomura, Hiroshi 1989 (Box 2)
          - N-O
            - Na, Tsung (Box 2)
            - Najiar, Mary Anne and William R. (Box 2)
            - Nederlander, Robert E. (Box 2)
            - Neel, J. V. (Box 2)
            - Neidhardt, Fred 1992 (Box 2)
            - Nunan, Rebecca and Carlton (Box 2)
            - Organski, A. F. K. (Box 2)
          - P
            - Palmer, J. (Box 2)
            - Papes, Jr., Theodore C. (Box 2)
            - Parker, John (Box 2)
            - Patrides, C. A. (Box 2)
            - Pattullo, Andrew (Box 2)
            - Pearson (Box 2)
            - Pecoraro (Box 2)
            - Penner-Hahn (Box 2)
            - Peters, J. (Box 2)
            - Petters, Robert (Box 2)
            - Pierce, William J. (Box 2)
            - Pinsky, Nicole (Box 2)
            - Potter, Robert A. (Box 2)
            - Pulgram, Ernst (Box 2)
          - R
            - Reed, John W. (Box 2)
            - Richart, F. E. 1980 (Box 2)
            - Rine, Nicolas 1989 (Box 2)
            - Roach, Thomas (Box 2)
          - S
            - Sandalow, Terrance (Box 2)
            - Sax, Joe (Box 2)
            - Senior, Thomas (Box 2)
            - Sessions, William 1989 (Box 2)
            - Severence, D. (Box 2)
            - Scheer, C. Ruby (Box 2)
            - Scheer, James H. (Box 2)
            - Schlosser, Peter 1989 (Box 2)
            - Schottenfeld (Box 2)
            - Schoem, David 1988 (Box 2)
            - Schultz, Albert B. 1983 (Box 2)
            - Schultz, Amy (Box 2)
            - Shapiro, Harold T. (Box 2)
            - Shattenfeld (Box 2)
            - Shogren, Cliff (Box 2)
            - Simpson, A. W. (Box 2)
            - Sinai, Nathan 1974 (Box 2)
            - Skadden 1975 (Box 2)
            - Smith, Allan F. (Box 2)
            - Smith, Roger B. (Box 2)
            - Spivey, Allen (see also Terpstra) (Box 2)
            - St. Antoine, Theodore J. 1984 (Box 2)
            - Standifter, James (Box 2)
            - Stanley, Albert A. (Box 2)
            - Starr, Chester (Box 2)
            - Stein, Louise 1990 (Box 2)
            - Stirton, William E. 1967 (Box 2)
            - Suny, Ronald (Box 2)
          - T
            - Takeda, Jeanne (Box 2)
            - Taylor, F. M. (Box 2)
            - Taylor, James (Box 2)
            - Taylor, Jane (Box 2)
            - Taylor, S. Martin (Box 2)
            - Terpstra (Box 2)
            - Thiry, James R. (Box 2)
            - Thomas, Laurita (Box 2)
            - Thompson, Norman W. (Box 2)
            - Tracey, Elaine (Box 2)
            - Trostel, John M. (Box 2)
            - Trow (Box 2)
            - Turcotte, Jeremiah (Box 2)
            - Twitchell, Mary 1989 (Box 2)
          - Unidentified Portraits (Box 2)
          - V
            - Vander Haagen, A. (Box 2)
            - Varian, Hal R. (Box 2)
            - Veidi, Gloria (Box 2)
            - Velleman, J. David 1984 (Box 2)
            - Veltman, Martinus J.G. (Box 2)
            - Vining, Joseph (Box 2)
            - Vinter, Robert (Box 2)
          - W
            - Waggoner, Lawrence W. (Box 2)
            - Wagner, J.G. (Box 2)
            - Walgreen, Charles and Jean (Box 2)
            - Ward, Marcus (Box 2)
            - Ward 1982 (Box 2)
            - Warren, Austin 1961 (Box 2)
            - Warren, Rich (Box 2)
            - Watkins, Glenn 1976 (Box 2)
            - Webster, Duane E. (Box 2)
            - Wehmeyer, Lewis E. (Box 2)
            - Weisbuch, Bob (Box 2)
            - Whitaker, Jr., Gilbert R. 1979 (Box 2)
            - White, James B. (Box 2)
            - White, James J. (Box 2)
            - White, Katherine E. (Box 2)
            - White, Patricia (Box 2)
            - Wilder, Raymond L. 1966 (Box 2)
            - Wright, L. Hart (Box 2)
          - Y-Z
            - Yamada (Box 2)
            - Yih, Chia-Shun (Box 2)
            - Zajonc, Robert (Box 2)
            - Zumberge, Cathy and Mark (Box 2)
      - Subject Files
        - Aerial Views, circa 1960-1984 (Box 2)
        - Alumni Center, 1983-c.1986 (Box 2)
        - Angell Hall, 1972-c.1995 (Box 2)
        - School of Art and Design, 1974-c.1979 (Box 2)
        - Asia Library (Box 2)
        - Athletic Campus (Box 2)
        - Band 1980s (Box 2)
        - Bentley Historical Library 1973-1983 (Box 2)
        - Bicycles (Box 2)
        - Biological Chemistry, 1972-c.1990 (Box 2)
        - Bookstore (negatives only) (Box 2)
        - Buhr Building 1995 (Box 2)
        - Building Models, 1961-c.1995 (Box 3)
        - Burton Tower (Box 3)
        - Business School, circa 1970-1990 (Box 3)
        - Campus Scenes (Box 3)
        - Celebrities
          - Includes: (Box 3)
          - Blanchard, James (Box 3)
          - Carter, Jimmy (Box 3)
          - Cliburn, Van (Box 3)
          - Faust, William (Box 3)
          - Ford, Gerald (Box 3)
          - Gumble, Bryant (Box 3)
          - Hope, Bob (Box 3)
          - Miller, Arthur (Box 3)
          - Scott, Willard (Box 3)
        - Center for the Education of Women (Box 3)
        - Chemical Science 1986-1987 (Box 3)
        - Chemical Engineering 1987 (Box 3)
        - Chemistry (Box 3)
        - Children 1970s-1980s (Box 3)
        - Classical Studies (Box 3)
        - Clements Library (Box 3)
        - Commencement 1961-1991 (Box 3)
        - Computers, 1982-c.1995 (Box 3)
        - Credit Union (Box 3)
        - Cultural Events (Box 3)
        - Dearborn Campus 1978-1990s (Box 3)
        - Dentistry 1970s-1980s (Box 3)
        - Dining (Box 3)
        - Diversity, 1972-c.1990 (Box 3)
        - Dow Buildings (Box 3)
        - School of Education, 1974-c.1980 (Box 3)
        - College of Engineering 1982-1987 (Box 3)
        - Engineering Library, c.1985 (Box 3)
        - Event, Panel on Europe 1992 (Box 3)
        - Exhibit Museum 1983-1994 (Box 3)
        - Fleming Administration Building (Box 3)
        - Flint Campus 1980s (Box 3)
        - Gerald R. Ford Library (Box 3)